# VITALII ZHUKOV, PHD

346 332 8210 ZHUKO.V.ITALY@GMAIL.COM VVZHUKOV.GITHUB.IO

#### **SUMMARY**

More than 12 years of experience in Data Science, Software Engineering, and Project Management in a number of different domains including: research, telecommunications, banking, and security. Research focus is in the areas of large language models, human performance, computational physiology, and monitoring systems.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

2019 - Present

#### AI/ML Researcher

CS Department, Computational Physiology Laboratory

- Stack: Python (PyTorch, Keras, TensorFlow), MySQL, PostgreSQL, GPT-3.5, Llama2, ALBERT, R (tidyverse, dplyr, car, lme4, caret, MASS, shiny, ggplot2, plotly), Hugging Face, MPI, Open MPI, CUDA.
- Led 3 research projects, examining laws underlying human behavior and achievement in highly competitive environments resulting in two journal manuscripts and two conference presentations.
- Designed novel analytical method (data quality control for skewed distributions). Applied inferential tools and fine-tuned large language models for hypothesis testing, classification, and forecasting.
- Taught 3 graduate-level classes: Statistical Methods in Research, Ubiquitous Computing, Data Structures and Algorithms to more than 2000 students in Computer Science department.
- Developed a web-based system to collect, analyze, and visualize user surveys and performance data, optimizing course complexity and flow (4 semesters data, ~500 weekly surveys).

2017 - 2018

## Project Manager (R&D)

Luxoft / Deutsche Bank

- Managed 3 teams comprising 53 engineers and data scientists, ensuring delivery of projects in the security domain.
- Participated in the successful execution of two Proof of Concept initiatives for two new products (user studies, concept/usability testing).
- Collaborated with various business and product teams to prioritize hypotheses and research questions in strategic planning. Participated in design evaluation.

2010 - 2017

#### Head of Automation (R&D)

General Satellite

- Created and led the Automation Department (4 FTE): monitoring, forecasting, and tools development.
- Designed and implemented a customer behavior analytics system, improving customer segmentation models (12.5 million users). Strengthened behavior analysis capabilities (customer research), enhancing strategic planning resulting in 8% revenue increase.
- Developed and deployed enterprise-scale monitoring system (2000+ hosts, 3m+ metrics).

#### **SKILLS**

- Python; R; SQL; C++; Bash.
- GCP; CloudConsole; LangChain; VertexAI; DialogflowCX; DataFlow; DataFusion; LookerML; BigQuery.
- ML; DL; LLM System design; ELT; Prompt Design & Engineering; RAG.
- Git; Atlassian Jira/Confluence; Redmine; OSF; Zabbix; ITIL; SDLC; Agile; Scrum.

#### **CERTIFICATIONS & DIPLOMAS**

2014	Zabbix Certified Specialist Zabbix, Credential ID CS-141077
2014 – 2015	Database Development and Administration Peter the Great St. Petersburg Polytechnic University, GPA: 4.0
2015	Python Software Development ITMO University, GPA 4.0
2016	ITIL Foundation v3 Eurika, Learning center
2016	Automating Administration with Windows PowerShell Eurika, Learning center, 10961B
2018	Data Science Specialization Johns Hopkins University, Coursera
2020	Information Privacy and Security (IPS) CITI Program, Credential ID 39951557
2020	Responsible Conduct of Research for Engineers CITI Program, Credential ID 39951088
2020	Conflict of Interest in Research CITI Program, Credential ID 39951556
2024	Artificial Intelligence, Cybersecurity, Data Fundamentals IBM SkillsBuild
2023 – 2024	GCP, VertexAl, Generative Al, Conversational Al, Looker, LookerML Google CloudSkillBoost

### **EDUCATION**

#### Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.)

Computer Science, University of Houston, GPA 3.9

## Master of Science (M.S.)

Mechanical Engineering, Peter the Great St. Petersburg Polytechnic University

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

[IN PREPARATION] **Zhukov**, Tsiamyrtzis, Pavlidis (2024) Modeling of Competitive Human Performance. [UNDER REVIEW] **Zhukov**, Pavlidis, Dukes (2023) Quantitative History of Affectivism. [CONFERENCE PAPER] **Zhukov** et al. (2022) Convergence in Affective Sciences, ISRE 2022, LA CA. [CONFERENCE PAPER] Hasan, Tsiamyrtzis, **Zhukov**, Manser, Wunderlich, Pavlidis (2023) ACM CHI 2024. [PUBLISHED] Zhukova, Li, **Zhukov**, Grigorenko (2023) Children, 10(8), p.1367. [BLOG] Personal technical blog, https://vvzhukov.github.io